[Man Narrating] All my life, I've lived and worked in the big city,
配音：伍迪・艾伦
配音：吉恩・哈克曼
配音：珍妮弗・洛佩斯
配音：西尔维斯特・史泰龙 莎朗・斯通
我这辈子都住在大城市
老实说，这是个问题
which, now that I think of it, is kind of a problem,
since I always feel uncomfortable around crowds.
我一直不喜欢我住的地方
I mean it. I have this fear of enclosed spaces.
我很害怕封闭的空间
l-l-l... Everything makes me feel trapped all the time.
我...我...我老觉得被困住
You know, I always tell myself there's gotta be something better out there.
我一直告诉自己
一定有更好的地方
But maybe l... maybe I think too much.
但我还得面对现实
I-I-I think everything must go back to the fact...
that I had a very anxious childhood.
我想是因为我的童年不愉快
You know, my mother never had time for me.
你知道我母亲没时间陪我
When you're the middle child in a family of 5 million,
我是中间的小孩
有五百万个兄弟姐妹
you don't get any attention.
当然得不到宠爱
I mean, how is it possible?
怎么可能呢?
And-And I've always had these abandonment issues which plague me.
我老是觉得被父母遗弃
My father was-was basically a drone, like I've said.
我父亲是只雄蚁
And, you know, the guy flew away when I was just a larva.
我还是小蛹时他就飞走了
And my job, don't get me started on, because it really annoys me.
至于我的工作，更别提了
因为真的很无聊
I-I was not cut out to be a worker, I'll tell you right now.
老实说，我不适合当蚂蚁
I-I-I feel physically inadequate.
我的体力不够
My whole life, I've never been able to lift...
我从来都没办法
more than 10 times my own body weight.
搬比我重十倍的东西
And, when you get down to it, handling dirt is, you know... [Shudders]
老实说，玩泥巴
is not my idea of a rewarding career.
不能算是有成就感的事业
It's this whole gung ho, superorganism thing...
这种井井有条的组织
that... that, you know, I can't get.
我就是不习惯
I try, but I don't get it.
我试过，我就是不懂
I mean... What is it? I'm supposed to do everything for the colony.
我该为蚁国牺牲一切吗?
And-And what about my needs? What about me?
我的需要呢？我怎么办?
I've gotta believe there's someplace out there that's better than this.
我得相信外面有更好的世界
Otherwise, I would just curl up in a larval position and weep.
否则我干脆卷成一团哭死算了
[Sighs]
这整个制度都让我觉得...
The whole system makes me feel...
[Exhales] insignificant.
非常渺小
Excellent.
太好了，你终于有突破
- You've made a real breakthrough. - I have?
是吗?
Yes, Z. You are insignificant.
没错，
I am?
你的确很渺小
真的吗?
蚁哥正传
** [Whistling]
[Man] Ground floor.
一楼到了
[Babies Crying Softly]
- [Cries] - Uh, worker.
工蚁
Soldier.
兵蚁
Ooh. [Giggles]
- Uh-oh. - Worker.
工蚁
[Cries]
[Man] Let's try it again.
大家再试一次
Firm grip. Swing hard. Back straight. Concentrate.
抓紧，用力，背挺直
专心一点，打起精神
Follow through.
[Grunts]
Okay. I've got to keep a positive attitude.
好吧，我得保持乐观
A good attitude, even though I'm utterly insignificant.
看开点，虽然我很渺小
I'm-I'm insignificant, um, but with attitude.
我很渺小，可是很有个性
- [Coughs] - [Woman] 0h, sorry, Z.
抱歉，Z
- [Chuckles] I didn't see ya. - Great, Azteca.
我没看到你
It's working already. I'm so meaningless, I'm invisible.
太好了，小爱，有用了
我太渺小，简直不存在
- [Grunts] - [Laughs]
Now, you're getting it.
你终于搞懂了
After all, it's not about you.
毕竟...
...你并不重要
It's about us... the team.
我们才重要
团队精神
It's about... this.
一切都是为了...这个
Uh, a giant hole in the ground?
地底下的大洞?
- Okay, people. Are we feeling good? - [All] Yeah.
大伙，你们好吗?
好
- Yeah. - Great.
很好
Now, R-1734 through Z-7829, you guys are on wrecking ball.
太好了
R―1734到Z―7829
你们当大球
- You got it. - Swell.
没问题
- You got it. - [Man] All right. Swing time.
棒呆了
没问题
- Let's get physical. - I love this job.
记住，想象你是球
Now, remember, Azteca, "Be the ball."
That's the main thing. Now, remember that.
记住这个重点
You know, gotta be one with the ball.
和球合而为一
Would you cut it out already?
别闹了
Jeez. I love my work. And you, well...
我很爱我的工作，你...
You think too much.
你想太多了
Come on, Z. Help us build a bigger, better colony.
帮我们建设更好更大的蚁国
And, for cryin' out loud, try to be happy about it.
拜托你开心点
Sure, you know. I mean, why-why...
是啊
我自愿撞墙，当然开心了
How could I possibly be unhappy being a piece of construction equipment?
- Okay, workers, remember. - Here it comes.
工蚁们，记住
来了
- Be the ball. - 0h!
和球合而为一
[Foreman] Let the energy flow through you.
释放你们的能量
Grin and bear it. This is... This is for the colony. 0h.
咬紧牙关，这是为了国家
- [All Yelling] - 0w. This is...
这样肯定会吃上官司
This is just a lawsuit waiting to happen.
抓紧，开始了
- Hang on. Here we go. - Faster. Harder.
开始摆荡
Did I happen to mention that heights make me nauseous?
我有没有提过我有惧高症
没有
更好玩
No.
- This is a ball. - Hey.
- [Yelling, Indistinct] - [Gagging]
- [Azteca] Oh, Z. - Yes. Yes. I understand.
Z
我知道，我搞砸了
I dropped the ball.
[Man] Workers. They're weak.
工蚁，他们太软弱了
They lack discipline. They lack commitment.
缺乏纪律，没有决心
General, I know there's been a glitch or two.
将军：我知道出了点小差错
But everybody is working full tilt as it is, and...
不过大家都尽了全力
You can't help it, it's your nature.
没办法，工蚁就是无能
But in spite of your limitations,
这是你们的天性
you are going to finish this tunnel on schedule.
不过你要按时完成隧道
Come hell or high water.
不管发生什么事
Anyone who falls behind is going to have to explain themselves to Colonel Cutter.
进度落后就得向卡特上校交代
卡特上校可没我这么好说话
And let me assure you, the colonel is not as understanding as I am.
Dismissed.
解散
Four more days, Cutter. Four more days.
还剩四天，卡特
Then we can bid final farewell to their kind of incompetence.
就能永远摆脱这一群蠢蛋
Yes, sir.
是，长官
A fresh start.
从新开始
- Imagine it! - A strong colony, sir.
想想看
一个强大的国家
A colony we can be proud of.
我们引以为傲的国家
Yes, but we're not there yet.
不过还没成功
Cutter, we just got word that a termite army has mobilized against us.
卡特
根据情报，白蚁要攻打我们
Against us?
攻打我们?
We'll have to send troops deep into hostile territory...
我们得派军队攻打白蚁巢穴
to attack their colony.
攻打白蚁?这简直是自杀
Attack a termite colony, sir?
- That's suicide. - Exactly.
正是，我要的名单呢?
- Do you have the list I asked for? - Yes, General.
在这儿，将军
These are the units loyal to the queen.
这些是忠于蚁后的军队
Hm. Then they're the ones we'll be sending.
那就派他们出战
It's a shame. There's some fine officers here.
可惜，他们是优秀军人
Don't we need the queen's approval to declare war?
只有蚁后才能宣战
0ur very next stop, Cutter.
我正要去找她
General, we've been at peace with that colony for years.
将军，我们和白蚁相安无事
- Why would they attack us? - They want our land.
他们为何要开战?
They're desperate for more foraging territory.
为了我们的土地
他们想扩大领土
Perhaps they think we've grown soft or weak.
他们大概以为我们好欺负
Why don't we dispatch an ambassador, negotiate a new treaty?
不如派名使者拟订和平条约
- We don't need to send soldiers. - Believe me.
不必牺牲士兵
Every ant in this colony is so precious to me.
相信我
我爱惜每只蚂蚁的性命
- [Grunts] - That's why we must strike now.
所以才要让敌人措手不及
We have the element of surprise.
If the termite shock troops enter our colony, well...
要是让白蚁改进来
Yes, General, I know what they can do to us.
是的，将军
我知道他们的手段
- Very well. - You've made a wise decision.
好吧
这是英明的决定
In fact, you've insured the future of this colony.
你确保了蚁国的未来前途
Hello, General.
你好，将军
Princess Bala. What a nice surprise.
芭拉公主，很高兴见到你
You look lovelier each time I see you.
你是越来越标致了
Thanks. I hope you're not just here on business.
谢谢
希望你不只是来谈公事
Oh, of course... [Chuckles] of course not.
当然...当然不是
Because, um, it might be nice...
因为我想在我们成亲之前...
if we had a conversation once before we get married.
...找机会跟你聊聊
You're absolutely right.
你说得很对
Cutter, schedule some private time for me and Princess Bala.
卡特，替我和公主挪出时间
Uh, in fact, sir, there is time right now for a personal moment.
现在你就有点私人时间
We're a few seconds ahead of schedule.
进度超前了几秒钟
Excellent. Princess.
太好了
公主
Well, a few seconds isn't much,
几秒钟不算久
but I guess if it's quality time...
我猜只要能好好聊聊
So, how was your day?
你今天好吗?
- Anything interesting happen? - We declared war.
发生什么趣事?
我们向白蚁宣战
Declared war?
宣战?
Boy, talk about a rough day.
真是的，好辛苦的一天
Sir, I hate to interrupt, but time stands still for no ant.
长官，恕我打岔
蚂蚁的时间很宝贵
公主
Princess.
Mom, could you remind me, why am I marrying this guy?
母后，拜托你提醒我
我为什么要嫁给他?
Bala, do we have to argue about this again?
芭拉，你又要跟我吵吗?
We don't seem to have anything in common. The guy's a stiff.
我们没有共同点，他好死板
Yes, darling. I know the general may be...
没错，我知道将军有点古板
a little gruff and somewhat overbearing at times,
有时候傲慢无礼
but I know that he cares about you.
不过他很关心你
He's just not particularly good at showing it.
他只是不太会表达
But you should've seen how persistently he asked for your hand in marriage.
他可是费尽心思要娶你为妻
But why me?
为什么?
Because you're the one who has to continue my work.
因为你必须继续我的工作
It's your place, dear.
这是你的责任
- What if I don't like my place? - Everyone has their place, Bala...
我不喜欢这责任呢
每只蚁都有自己的责任
you, the soldiers, the workers.
你，兵蚁和工蚁
当公主没那么糟，对吧?
Now, it's not all that bad being princess, is it?
难道你想成天搬泥土吗?
Would you prefer to be carting around dirt all day?
母后，别这么夸张
Mother, don't be so dramatic.
At least, they seem to have some fun every now and then.
不过至少他们偶尔能找点乐子
- [Man] Two aphid beers. - Why'd I have to be born a worker?
两杯蚜虫啤酒
我为什么生来就是工蚁?
You soldiers get all the glory, plus you get to go out in the world.
当兵最威风，还能到处跑
You meet interesting insects, you get to kill them.
认识有趣的昆虫，杀死它们
Yeah. But you get to spend all day with those...
是啊，不过你们成天都能...
beautiful worker girls.
跟漂亮的女士工蚁在一起
Weaver, they're career girls. They're obsessed with digging.
老魏，她们是上班女郎
只会成天挖泥土
[Sighs] I don't think I'm ever gonna meet the right girl for me.
我是碰不到梦中情人了
Who said a girl for you? I was talking about a girl for me.
我不是说你，我是说我
[Chuckles] Don't you want your aphid beer?
你不喝蚜虫啤酒吗?
Call me crazy, but... [Clears Throat]
别说我怪
我不从别人的屁眼喝东西
I have a thing about drinking from the anus of another creature. 0kay?
Suit yourself.
随你便
Ahhh. Me, I'm cuttin' loose.
我要好好轻松一下
We got royal inspection comin' up.
马上就要举行阅兵典礼
Inspection, meaning you're gonna stand around like an idiot...
阅兵典礼?
像白痴排排站让贵族嘲笑?
while a bunch of blue bloods smirk at you.
你怎么能忍受呢?
I don't know how you put up with it, Weaver.
我们认识很久了，对吧?
Z, I've known you for a long time. Right?
Definitely. You were born two seconds after me.
当然，你比我晚生两秒钟
Yeah. And ever since we were little, I've been listenin' to you complain.
我从小就听你抱怨
What are you bitching about?
你有什么好抱怨的?
In case you haven't noticed, we ants are running the show.
咱们蚂蚁统治了整个世界
We're the lords of the Earth.
我们是地球的主宰
Hey. Don't talk to me about earth, okay?
别跟我提到地球
'Cause I just spent all day hauling it around.
我整天都在搬地上的泥土
[Sighs] There's just gotta be a better place.
一定有更好的地方
There is. I've been there.
当然有，我去过
I'm sor... I'm sorry. Were you talking to me?
抱歉，你在跟我说话?
There is a better place... Insectopia.
有更好的地方
昆虫乐国
Oh, really. Lunatic at 3:00.
真的吗?
三点钟方向
You can't understand till you go there and see it yourself.
你得去亲眼目睹才会相信
You can be your own ant there.
在那里自由自在
The streets are paved with food.
到处都是吃的
Nobody tellin' you what to do.
没有人管你
No wars. No colony.
没有战争，没有国家
- I shoulda never left. - [Chuckles] 0h, yeah. Fascinating.
我不该离开的
有意恩
We were on a long-range recon. I got cut off from my unit.
我参加探敌行动，不小心脱队
Nothing like post-traumatic stress disorder to make your day complete.
我看他是个精神错乱的老兵
- Then I saw it... Insectopia! - Hey!
然后我就看到，昆虫乐国
You head towards the monolith.
朝着高山前进
Ten clicks past the great canyons to the land of red and white.
越过大峡谷和一片红白之地
Hey, gramps. You've had enough for one night.
老爹，你喝多了
Come on. Before you get in trouble.
来吧，别惹麻烦
Head for the monolith. Listen to me!
听我说，朝着高山前进
The monolith!
[Chuckles] That guy's got a screw loose.
那家伙头壳坏了
- Cross the lake! - Insectopia. [Scoffs]
划过大湖
昆虫乐国
Wouldn't it be great if it were that easy?
豆有这么容易就好了
- [Chuckles] Yeah. Dream on, Z. - Cross the lake.
是啊
继续作梦吧
Look for the land of red and white.
找到那片红白之地
Wow! This is so... gritty.
这地方真是...
Ten minutes and we're out of here. Right? This place is off limits.
...有够俗
只能持十分钟，这是禁地
Just blame it on me. Say it was all my idea.
怪我吧，就说这是我的主意
- It is all your idea. - Besides, no one's gonna recognize us.
本来就是你的主意
没有人会认得我们的
Come on, girls. What do you say?
来吧，怎么样?
Let's take a walk on the wild side.
让我们去野一下吧
[Man On Loud Speaker] 0kay, everybody. 6:15. Time to dance.
大伙儿，六点半，该跳舞了
- Time to cut a rug, Z. - 0h, no. That's okay.
跳舞吧，Z
不了，我不想磨破我的鞋子
I'm gonna leave the rug just the way it is, Weaver.
** [Jazz, Slow]
Step back, ladies.
你们让开
I'm gonna ask one of these workers to dance with me.
我要邀请一只工蚁陪我跳舞
0h.
What a bunch of losers.
这些蚂蚁逊毙了
Mindless zombies capitulating to an oppressive system.
就象一群受到压迫的僵尸一样
- Hi. Want to dance? - Absolutely.
嗨，想跳舞吗?
当然想
Follow me.
跟我来
So, how come I haven't seen you around here before?
那...我怎么没见过你
0h, I don't get out much.
我不常出来玩
I, uh, I work over at the palace.
我在皇宫工作
Oh, the palace, huh? I bet those royals really live it up.
皇宫吗?
Course they're all a little... you know... from inbreeding.
皇亲贵族一定夜夜笙歌
他们都近亲交配，有点那个...
What?
什么?
Yowch!
Ya-Ya... Yowch! Yowch.
- Yowch. - What on earth are you doing?
你在跳什么舞?
Well, actually, to tell you the truth, I'm sort of making it up.
老实说，我是边跳边想
Really?
真的吗?
Why does everybody have to dance the same way?
为什么大家都跳同一种舞
That's completely boring. It's... It's monotonous.
真是无聊透顶
单调枯燥
It's no fun.
一点都不好玩
** [Orchestra: Latin, Up-Tempo]
Hey. Watch your step, worker.
小心点，工蚁
You watch yours, buddy, or you'll be in big trouble.
你才小心点，我会要你好看
Th-Th-That's okay. I'll... I'm gonna let him off this time.
没关系，这次我饶过他
What? Are you crazy? This guy's built like a pebble.
你疯啦?他壮得像头牛
Aren't you even gonna defend yourself?
你不自卫吗?
Hey, buddy. Get back in place.
小子，回到你的位置
- Me? Uh... Uh... - What if he doesn't want to?
我?
他不想回去呢?
[Clears Throat] Yeah. What if I don't like my place?
是呀，我不喜欢我的位置
- What's he talkin' about? - We got us a troublemaker.
他在说什么?
Buckle up, Spanky.
小麻烦鬼
等死吧，臭小子
This one goes out to all the lazy workers.
我要教训你这只懒惰虫
[Grunts]
你最好别这么嚣张
You ought to watch that aggressive behavior, buddy.
He's just a worker. [Muffled Talking]
他是只工蚁
- [Ants Shouting] - [Chuckles]
Princess Bala! Princess Bala! The guards are coming.
芭拉公主
公主，侍卫赶来了
- Let's get outta here. - Wait.
快走吧
等等
[Shouting, Indistinct]
公主?你是公主?
Princess? You're a princess?
Uh, I gotta go.
我得走了
- When can I see you again? - Let me think. Never.
我几时能再见到你?
我想想看
- Bye. - No. Wait.
永远不能，再见
等一下
[Grunts]
[Z] * What a day it has been *
今天真美妙，我心在乱跳
* What a rare mood I'm in *
* Why, it's almost like being in love *
我好象是坠入爱河
- * There's a smile * - Huh?
我面带微笑，心里在大叫
* On my face for the whole insect race *
我好象是坠入爱河
* Why, it's almost like being in love **
[Whistle Blows]
Yowch.
[Talking, Indistinct]
- Can I get you another one, pal? - [Sighs] No, thanks.
你要再来一杯吗?
不要
- I think I'm gonna go. - Yeah. I don't blame you.
谢了，我要走了
我不怪你
It's always slow in here the night before one of those royal reviews.
阅兵典礼前晚总是很冷清
兵蚁见蚁后前想好好的睡一睡
I guess the soldiers need their shut-eye before they meet the queen.
很正常
这就对了
- I don't blame ya. - That's it!
我以前也是...
You know, I was once... See ya.
回头见
[Snoring]
Psst. Weaver.
老魏
I figured it out. Weaver. Weaver.
我有办法了，老魏...
What? What?
什么?
- [Clears Throat] - I got a great idea.
我有个好点子
You gotta switch places with me. Let me go to the inspection instead of you.
我们交换身份，我去参加阅兵
- What time is it? - Weaver. The royal family will be there.
现在几点钟?
皇室成员都会在
This is the only way I can see her.
这样我才能见到她
- See who? - Princess Bala.
见到谁?
芭拉公主
Are you nuts?
你疯啦?
You want me to switch places with you?
你要跟我交换身份
Do you know how much trouble you can get into...
光是提到假扮兵蚁就有麻烦
for even talkin' about impersonatin' a soldier?
You can get in trouble just for listenin'...
连听到假扮兵蚁的事都有麻烦
to someone talkin' about impersonatin' a soldier.
You have to help me.
你得帮帮我
If I can't see her again, my life is not worth living.
我见不到她就活不下去
Pl-Pl-Please, Weaver. Please.
求求你，老魏
Switch jobs with me just for a day.
跟我交换身份，一天就行
Th-Think of all the things that I've done for you.
想想我帮了你多少忙
Hm. I can't think of any.
我想不出来
Okay. So, think of all the things that I'm gonna do for you.
好吧
想想这有多少好处
Would I meet some worker girls?
能认识女工蚁吗?
Are you kidding? They always go after the new guy.
当然能，她们最爱新工蚁
It's like a sport for them.
这是她们的嗜好
And-And believe me, they will definitely go...
相信我
她们肯定喜欢你这个大帅哥
- for an adorable little insect like you. - Mmm.
Weaver, l... I have to see her again.
我一定要见到她
Z, what kind of chance do you have with a princess?
你怎么配得上公主
I mean, she probably won't even remember you.
她大概都不记得你
[Sighs] l... I know it sounds nuts, but I have to try.
你一定觉得我疯了
不过我得试试看
Oh, boy. [Exhales]
老天爷
- ** [March] - Princess, fancy meeting you here.
公主，没想到会见到你
What do you say we lose this crowd?
跟我单独聚聚如何
Oh, me? You know, l... I wear many hats.
我?我是多才多艺
I guess you'd have to call me a Renaissance ant.
我是所谓的“蚁”才
[Man] Eyes right!
向右看齐
- Beautiful! Just beautiful! - Mm.
太美了，太美了
整齐一排，井井有条
- The precision. The order. - 0h.
芭拉公主...
Princess Bala! Princess Bala! Hey. It's me.
是我
Remember Z from the bar?
记得吗?酒吧的Z
Princess Bala! Princess Bala! Princess...
芭拉公主...
Bala, you must encourage the troops.
芭拉，你要鼓励他们
Wave.
挥手
Oh. She sees me. Excuse me, guys. l-l... Sorry.
她看到我
借过...那边风景比较好
I just got a better offer. Could you excu...
立正
Company halt!
公主...
Princess. Princess Bala.
芭拉公主
Quiet there! Get back in rank.
安静，马上归队
- You new, kid? - 0h, y-yes, but I'm gettin' out soon.
你是新兵吗?
对，不过我马上退伍
I got a trial membership.
我只是试用会员
Trial membership. [Chuckles] That's a good one!
试用会员，真好笑
- Name's Barbatus. - Z.
我叫巴贝塔
我是Z
- Right face! - Psst.
向右转
- [Footsteps] - [Whip Cracks]
Sacrifice. To some, it is just a word.
为国牺牲
有些人认为只是句口号
To others, it is a code.
有些人将它视为使命
- Jeez. I'm really bad at word games. - [Chuckles]
我也搞不懂
兵蚁知道个人性命微不足道
A soldier knows that the life of an individual ant doesn't matter.
只有国家最重要
What matters is the colony.
为蚁国而生，为蚁国而战
He's willing to live for the colony, to fight for the colony,
to die for the colony.
为蚁国而死
- This guy's crazy. - I hear ya.
这家伙秀逗了
说得好
八点整
At 0800 hours, we received word that the termite enemy has mobilized.
白蚁军团全体动员
We have no choice but to launch a preemptive strike.
我们只有先下手为强
You are the queen's finest.
你们是蚁后最优秀的士兵
I know you will all do you duty.
一定全力以赴
I am proud to send you into battle.
我很荣幸派你们上战场
Into... I'm sor-I'm sorry. Into battle?
什么?上战场?
- Dismissed. - [Man] Left face. Forward march.
解散
向左转
齐步向前走
You know, I think there's been a terrible mistake.
一定是搞错了
You know, the truth is I just... I just came for the speech.
我只是来听演讲的
Don't worry, kid. I'll watch out for ya.
别怕，小子，我会照顾你
- Sound off. - One! - Two!
报数
一...二...
- Sound off. - Three! - Huh?
报数
三
- Sound off. - Five!
报数
五...六...七...八...
- Six! - Seven!
- Eight! - Nine!
- Ten! - Eleven!
- Twelve! - Thirteen!
* We ants go marching one by one Hurrah, hurrah *
我们勇敢地前进，万岁万岁
[All] * We slaughter termites just for fun, hurrah, hurrah *
消灭邪恶的白蚁，万岁万岁
- So, these termites, they're-they-re... - ** [Continues, Indistinct]
白蚁不是我们的对手
These guys aren't gonna put up much of a fight? We're talkin' pushovers, right?
我们赢定了，对吧?
Not really, kid. They're five times our size.
不对，白蚁比蚂蚁大五倍
And they shoot acid from their foreheads.
还会喷出硫酸
[Gasps]
矮子，快走
- [Grunts] - Hey. Keep it movin', shorty.
[All] * We ants go marching two by two Hurrah, hurrah *
我们勇敢地前进，万岁万岁
不怕困难不怕死，万岁万岁
* We'll all be dead before we're through Hurrah, hurrah *
- ** [Humming] - Say, what exactly does our platoon do?
我们的部队做什么?
I mean, will we be serving beverages or processing paperwork?
准备伙食还是处理公文?
Our platoon has the best assignment... first into battle.
我们的任务最棒
Huh?
这是先锋部队
* We ants go marching three by three, hurrah, hurrah, hurrah, hurrah *
我们一个个前进，万岁万岁
万岁万岁!
* We're off to face our destiny Hurrah, hurrah *
勇敢地面对命运，万岁万岁
Hey. Wait a minute. Let's not get... We're being too hasty here.
慢着，我们太卤莽了
These... These guys sound like bruisers.
敌人这么厉害
Just how were you figuring on beating them?
该怎样打败他们?
Superior numbers, kid. Overwhelm their defenses and kill their queen.
用“蚁”海战术
冲破防线，消灭白蚁后
Hey, fellas. You're being a little extreme, I feel.
这么做太极端了
W-Why don't we try and influence their political process...
不如用政治现金收买他们
with campaign contributions?
I like you, kid. You got a sense of humor.
我喜欢你，你很幽默
Forward!
向前冲!
Come on. Let's kick some termite butt.
来吧，让白蚁们好看
0ver the top!
冲上山头
- [All Shouting, Indistinct] - Yeeow!
[Shouting Stops]
- Where is everyone? - Something's not right.
敌军呢?
不太对劲
Don't be scared, kid.
别怕，小子
- [Gasps] - [Growls]
他们在这里
Attack!
进攻
[Groans]
Come on.
来吧
- [Growls] - [Yells]
Barbatus, you saved my life.
巴贝塔，你救了我
Ah, don't get all sappy about it.
别跟我婆婆妈妈
- Hey, guys. Look out behind you! - [Growls]
大伙，小心后面
Hey... Hey, guys.
大伙，帮帮忙
Can somebody help me here? Can anybody... Hey.
Yeah.
好啊
[Grunting]
Okay, mama. [Grunts] Yeah.
棒呆了
Oh, yeah. Big guy comin' through. [Grunts]
我来也
I love it.
好爽
Hey. Hey. Hey. Take it easy, muscles.
别这么卖力，健美先生
You're makin' the rest of us look bad.
你总得休息一下吧
What happened to Z?
Z怎么了?
He's takin' a personal day, so I'm fillin' in.
他休假，让我代他的班
You fill in any more, and you'll explode.
你再挖下去就会爆炸
Eh, you got a problem?
你有问题吗?
No, uh... uh...
没有
Nobody told me digging was so much fun.
没有人说过挖土这么好玩
You know, you pick the dirt up. You move it.
把土挖起来，搬过去
You pick it up again. You move it again. Lots of reps.
再挖起来，然后搬过去
You exercise the arms and the thorax.
不断重复，锻练手臂和胸肌
Yes, l... I see what you mean.
我看得出来
- Um. Yeah. That is fascinating. - Sorry, sir.
太有意思了
I was just havin' a chat with my friend, sir.
抱歉，长官，我只是在聊天
You know, I just had a chat with General Mandible.
我刚才和曼将军聊过
Anybody who doesn't meet his quota is going to be downsized.
达不到标准的工蚁会被炒鱿鱼
Come on. Cut him a break. He's new.
放他一马吧
Hey. What do you say we help your attitude a little bit...
他是新来的
我不如给你一点教训
by taking away your rations for the day.
今天不让你吃饭
Thanks for your time.
谢谢你
I don't know what came over me.
我是哪根筋不对敢跟他顶嘴
Talking back like that.
I must be losin' it.
我一定是疯了
Sorry I got you in trouble.
抱歉害你惹麻烦，不过你可以
But, listen, you can... share my rations. Whoa.
和我一起...
If you want.
...分享食物
- Are you askin' me out to dinner? - [Chuckles]
你要请我吃饭?
0h, no. l...
不是啦
Well, if you don't have anything else planned.
要是你没别的事
[Laughs] I'll check my calendar.
我会查我的事历
You know,
老实说
I'm kinda glad Z's takin' a breather.
我很高兴Z今天体假
Kid!
小子
Kid, over here.
小子，这里
Barbatus.
马贝塔
Be honest, kid. Am I hurt bad?
老实说，我伤得重吗?
N-No. N-Not at all. You're... Actually, you're lookin' terrific.
一点都不重
你的伤势很轻
You got, you know, swell color in your cheeks.
脸色很不错
No. I can see it in your eyes.
不，我看得出来
I'm a goner.
我死定了
Help me up, Z.
扶我起来
[Sniffs] I can't feel my legs.
You gotta hang in there, buddy. I know you're gonna make it.
我的腿没有感觉
撑着点，老兄
你一定会活下去的
Just take... take deep breaths.
深呼吸
Because I'm gonna try and find your body.
我去找你的身体
It's bound to be out there somewhere.
一定是在...这附近
[Coughs, Sighs]
Barbatus, hang on.
撑着点
- B-Barbatus. - Don't make my mistake, kid.
巴贝塔
别像我一样，小子
Don't follow orders your whole life.
别想着别人的事
Think for yourself. [Sighs]
要替自己着想
Barbatus.
巴贝塔
[Cutter] We're on schedule. Work is completed on "A" section, sir.
我们赶上进度
A区已经完成
We're clearing a path through "D" section now.
现在正要凿穿D区
We need to push harder, Cutter. I want double shifts around-the-clock.
加把劲，日夜赶工
We can't afford to let up. Is that clear?
不得延误，明白吗?
- Crystal, sir. - Good.
明白，长官
- What about section... - Excuse me, sir.
很好
至于...
报告，长官
This had better be important.
你最好有要事
Well, it's about the termite battle, sir.
事关白蚁之役
The enemy was destroyed, but it was a disaster for our troops, as well.
敌军全数被歼灭
不过我军也死伤惨重
Well, that's terrible. Terrible.
真是不幸
There is good news, sir. 0ne soldier did make it back.
好消息是，有一名兵蚁生还
- No kidding. - What did you say?
真的还是假的?
你说什么
Word is spreading through the colony.
消息已经传开来
The queen requested a meeting with the war hero.
蚁后要见这名英雄
Damn! Good. Damn good.
他妈的
真他妈的好，让我来
Uh, I'll handle this.
[Footsteps Approaching]
恭喜你，小兵
- Congratulations, soldier. - [Clears Throat]
[Chuckles] Well, you're a little short for a war hero, aren't you?
你这战争英雄未免太矮
A war hero? Sir, I-I don't actually think that I'm a hero.
战争英雄?
我不觉得我是个英雄
Good. I don't like heroes.
很好，我不喜欢英雄
- But, sir. You don't understand. l... - [Crowd Cheering]
可是你不明白
“凯旋归国”
“一比零，我们赢了”
l... I didn't do anything.
我什么也没做
I mean, it was all horrible. It was just a massacre.
太可怕了，那是场屠杀
A-A massacre upon a massacre.
屠杀加上滥杀
That's good, soldier. Now, wave.
很好，挥手
There was nothing you could do, Weaver.
你也没办法，老魏
You didn't know they were going to war.
你不知道他们要打仗
I just feel horrible.
我好内疚
Poor Z. I should have never let him go.
可怜的Z
我不该让他去的
Wait a minute. That's no soldier. That's Z!
慢着，那不是兵蚁
那是Z
Z? The little guy made it! [Chuckles]
Z?
那小家伙没死
[Crowd Cheering]
Let's go, soldier.
走吧，小兵
As I was saying, son, you are an ant after my own heart.
我正在说，我很欣赏你
你带着微笑面对死亡挑战
An ant that looks death in the face and laughs.
Well, actually, the truth is,
老实说，我通常都躲起来
I-I generally just make belittling comments...
and snicker behind death's back. [Chuckles]
背地里说些笑话
General Mandible.
曼将军
Keep your comments to yourself. Let me do the talking.
别乱说话，让我来
[Yawns]
这位是女王陛下，蚁后
May I present Her Majesty the Queen.
Charmed. Charmed.
幸会，幸会
And the Royal Princess Bala.
以及芭拉公主
[Growls]
欢迎凯旋归国
Welcome home, soldier.
We cannot begin to express our gratitude for your heroic efforts.
我们非常感谢你英勇杀敌
The private has asked me to convey his most humble appreciation.
他要我向你表示最大的谢意
Please. Please. It was nothing really.
不必客气，这不算什么
Just your average run-of-the-mill valor...
我只是跟往常一样英明神武
and extraordinary courageousness, you know.
在战场上没有迟疑的余地
In the heat of battle, there's very little time to think.
只能奋不顾身杀敌
One must attack! Attack! Attack! [Chuckles]
- [Chuckles] Well, indeed. - [Muffled Talking]
是的
As you can see, Your Highness, the battlefield is still fresh in his mind.
陛下，他还是满脑子打仗
So, begging your pardon, but this is the perfect time to debrief the private.
恕我们失陪
我要请他报告战况
Oh, please, General. Not on our first date.
拜托，别这么着急
[Chuckles] Not on our first date.
Haven't I seen you somewhere before?
我好象见过你
Well, maybe. Then again, maybe not.
也许有，也许没有
And then... then again.
不过也许又有
- Yowch. - That's it! You're the guy from the bar.
没错，你是酒吧那家伙
- Don't... Shh. - Bar? What bar?
什么酒吧?
I danced with this guy at the bar the other night.
我跟这家伙在酒吧跳过舞
He was just a worker then.
那时候他是只工蚁
- What were you doing at a bar? - Precisely what I want to know.
你跑到酒吧干嘛?
我也想知道
No. This isn't about me.
别扯到我身上
I mean, look at this worker. Look what he's done.
这只工蚁成为小蚁雄兵
I think you're thinkin' of someone else. After all, I am a soldier.
你看错了，我是只兵蚁
Exactly. You were a worker.
没错
你以前是工蚁，现在变成英雄
But now, you're a war hero.
- He's a worker? - A worker danced with my fiancee?
他是工蚁?
跟我未婚妻共舞?
F-Fiancee? W-W-Wait a minute.
未婚妻?
等等，别想歪，我能解释
This is not how it looks. I can explain this.
Hey. She was the one making all the moves.
是她先勾引我的
Arrest him.
抓住他
H-Hey wait a minute. Take it easy. Can't we discuss this?
别激动，有事好商量
What are you doing? Let go of my daughter.
你在干嘛?放开我女儿
He's taking her hostage!
他把她当人质
不，不是
No. No. I'm not. I mean, yes, I am.
我是说，没错
别过来，否则她就死
One more step and then the princess gets it.
[Grunts] Let go of me!
放开我
Ow! Don't make me hurt her.
别运我杀了她
[Z Yelling]
[Both Screaming]
[Groans] 0h.
你在干嘛？变态佬?
What are you doing, you creep?
你是疯了吗?
Are you out of your puny little mind?
在那儿，快走...
[Man] There they are down there! Let's go. Move. Move. Move.
0h, good.
太好了
Here they come to rescue me and kill you.
他们会来救我
Kill?
然后杀了你
杀了我?
- Hey, you guys. - Stop it. Stop it.
大伙
住嘴，你干嘛?
- What are you tryin' to do? - Get off me, you little twerp!
放手，臭东西
What do you want to do? Throw away everything we've got?
别放弃这难得的自由
What're you waiting for?
你们等什么?
Hello. Guys.
大伙儿
- Huh? - What is it?
那是什么?
It's beautiful.
好美哦
Ridgeway, get out of there!
快逃吧
[Both Grunting]
[Exhales] [Sighs Softly]
- Oh. Don't worry. I'm okay. - You?
别担心，我没事
You're okay? Hey. Who cares about you?
你?你没事?
谁管你?我差点没命
- I almost died here. - Will you please calm down?
拜托你冷静点
You're not gonna let a little near-death experience ruin your mood, are you?
你逃过一命应该高兴才对
Hey. This is not a mood. You're not listening to me.
我没这个心情
你没有听
Where am I?
我在哪里?